The MBuild Architecture

This section is going to be very abstract and deal mostly with terminology. Sorry. But please bear with me. This is the section where I introduce the language I use to discuss MBuild's internal workings. Hopefully, a consistent terminology will mean that the rest of the manual will make more sense and be more helpful.

Targets and Rules

The basic unit of MBuild is the target. If you're a make user, you might be used to that just being a synonym for "file". In MBuild, the better association to make is "variable". Like a variable in a programming language, a target in MBuild has two important properties: a name and a value. You choose the name, and tell the runtime how its value should be determined. Continuing the analogy, MBuild can be thought of as a limited programming language in which every statement is a variable assignment. The value that gets assigned to a target is the result of running some function, called a rule. When you execute your program -- that is, run a build -- MBuild invokes those rule functions and returns a set of values to you.

In make syntax, you declare targets by entering them in a special file called Makefile. A target declaration looks like this:

target: dependency dependency dependency
        rule code

In MBuild syntax, you put target declarations in a file called Buildfile, and they look like this:

string_target = "a string"
bool_target = true
rule_target = RuleName[ dependency_1 dependency_2 dependency_3 ]

The first two examples ought to be self-explanatory: we just told MBuild what values we want the targets to have. Nice and simple; however, you will not use this form very often. Almost always, you will use the third term: the value of rule_target is the value returned by the rule function RuleName. The arguments to the rule function are also values, and they are called the target's dependencies. A dependency can be one of two kinds:

A literal value, like we saw above:

ruletarget2 = RuleName [ "literal string" true ]

A reference to another target:

ruletarget3 = RuleName [ deptargetname ]

In this case, before the ruletarget3 can be evaluated, deptargetname must be evaluated. This is because the function RuleName can only accept values as inputs, so a reference to the target deptargetname doesn't make sense unless a value has been assigned to the target.

MBuild's system is built around a simple guarantee: if the values of a target's dependencies do not change, the target's value -- the output of the rule function -- does not change either.

Why is this fact important? Say it takes a long time to calculate the value of ruletarget, but you need to check its value frequently. Let's give MBuild a cache -- when asked to evaluate a target, it stores away the output value for future reference. The first time you ask for ruletarget's value, MBuild needs to evaluate dependency_1, dependency_2, and dependency_3, then run the function RuleName. The next time around, MBuild reevaluates the dependencies. If they haven't changed, MBuild can just return the cached value for ruletarget, instead of having to run the time-consuming RuleName function all over again.

You probably see where this discussion is heading. Let's make the example more concrete:

myprogram.exe = CompileExe [ main.cs helper.cs ]

Here, main.cs and helper.cs aren't literal values, so they must be targets. They evaluate to a certain kind of value that I haven't mentioned before -- a file value, which unsurprisingly points to a file on disk. Here, main.cs points to a source file called main.cs. But be careful: there is no particular reason that the target called main.cs must point to the file called main.cs. A target's name doesn't affect its value -- the value of main.cs could just as well be a file called tricked.txt, or even a boolean. (This is something of an overstatement. MBuild provides a large infrastructure for guessing a target's value based on its name, so that you don't have to say "helper.cs points to a file called helper.cs" for every source file in your project. But you can always override this guessing if you need to.)

(Also, if you're worried, when I say that "main.cs points to the file main.cs", I don't mean that MBuild just encodes a simple filename. MBuild has a file abstraction layer that ensures that file references are always valid, no matter what the working directory is.)

Values

Let's discuss values in more depth. To begin with, you might be wondering what kinds of values MBuild supports. The answer is that there is no builtin list of kinds of values; MBuild merely defines a few important characteristics that values must have. (Internally, what this means is that each value can be represented as a subclass of a .NET type called Result.) However, in practice, there are only a few fundamental kinds of value that are commonly used in MBuild:

String. Just as in any other programming language, a string is a piece of text.

Boolean. Again, a boolean is exactly as you would expect. Either true or false.

File. A file value is a stored reference to a file on disk. MBuild abstracts this reference so that the same reference will be valid no matter what directory you run MBuild from.

Directory. Similar to a file reference, but for directories.

Dictionary. Also known as a hashtable. A list of associations between names and values, stored in one cohesive unit. This type of value can be used to construct more complex pieces of data.

(You might note that MBuild doesn't have builtin support for integers or floats. I haven't needed them yet, and don't expect to need them in the future.)

MBuild's file reference system is fairly simple. It basically requires that you work with absolute pathnames: /home/peter/src/mbuild/mbuild.exe instead of just mbuild.exe. However, absolute pathnames are not necessarily relative to the filesystem root; they can also be relative to the source root or the build root. The source root is the toplevel directory of the sources being built, and the build root is the toplevel directory where built files are stored. (Normally, these are the same place, but you can set up a build so that they are different. This feature is useful if you want several different versions of a build from the same source package -- say, compiling binaries for several different processor architectures all from the same sources.) This three-rooted system has a few benefits:

The meaning of a file reference is more clear: is it a source file, a built file, or a system file?

You can move your build directories without having to rebuild everything. This would not be possible with a single-rooted system.

The first point is particularly important. For instance, when you do the MBuild equivalent of a "make dist" ("mbuild -d" ) MBuild finds all the file references below the "source" root and copies them into the distribution. No need to manually keep track of which files to include in a distribution. And when you do the equivalent of a "make clean" ("mbuild -c") MBuild finds all the "built" file references and deletes the files off disk. No need to manually keep track of which files to clean, either. Cool!

Names

As I have said, one of the important features of MBuild is that you can use canned build rules instead of writing them from scratch every time. This is a good thing, but it presents a new problem: how do we name rules? We don't want different sets of rules to conflict with each other, but we don't want to have to use long, unwieldy names all the time. MBuild uses a classic solution: there is a hierarchichal namespace for naming rules. Each rule does have a long, unwieldy fully-qualified name: examples include "Core.Xml.XslProcess" or "Languages.CSharp.CompileExe". But you can tell MBuild to only pay attention to specific prefixes in this namespace. This is done in a way that will look familiar to anyone who's used the .NET framework before:

using [ Core.Xml ]

output.xml = XslProcess [ input.xml stylesheet.xsl ]

The using directive tells the MBuild parser to look inside a particular section of the namespace when trying to translate an unqualified name into a fully-qualified name. (Here, an unqualified name is any name not containing a period.) In the example above, the complete name of the rule being invoked is Core.Xml.XslProcess. You can, of course, use more than one namespace if you want:

using [ 
	Core.Xml 
	Tools.DocbookPdf
]

output.xml = XslProcess [ input.xml stylesheet.xsl ]

output.pdf = DocbookToPdf [ output.xml ]

Here, the fully-qualified name of the first rule is Core.Xml.XslProcess, while the fully-qualified name of the second rule is Tools.DocbookPdf.DocbookToPdf.

As you may suspect, the fully-qualified name of a rule is actually a name in .NET's global type namespace. The name Core.Xml.XslProcess corresponds to a class whose complete name is MBuildDynamic.Core.Xml.XslProcess. The MBuildDynamic. prefix is automatically prepended to the names used in MBuild, so that build rules are restricted to a specific subset of the type namespace. This allows rule authors to blithely use namespaces like "Core" or "Tools" without worrying about a conflict with other .NET classes unrelated to MBuild.

Bundles and Assemblies

But where does the rule implementation come from? It lives in a bundle, which is a specialized .NET assembly. If you're not familiar with .NET, an assembly is pretty much like a shared library or DLL. But .NET assemblies have some nice features that traditional shared libraries don't:

Like all .NET components, assemblies are not platform-specific. You can distribute them with your project source, for instance.

Assemblies are completely standalone: code, support files and metadata are embedded directly into a single file. You can just copy a single assembly file around and it will be useful. So you don't need to distribute extra files like mkinstalldirs or ltmain.sh separately from the build logic.

Assemblies have a framework for versioning and digital signing built in, so there's already an infrastructure for verifying a set of build rules and making sure it doesn't conflict with existing rules.

The Global Assembly Cache, or GAC, provides a central repository of assemblies indexed by name and version. It's a core element of the .NET framework, so the GAC is the canonical place from which assemblies as loaded. This means that there's no worrying about what prefix new bundles should be installed in, etc. It also provides a robust framework for keeping track of multiple version of an assembly. (To be excessively precise, the GAC is also indexed by a cryptographic public key embedded into the assembly, but that's not really relevant right now.)

A bundle is just an assembly that exports subclasses of certain types and has a few special attributes. When we speak of loading bundles, accessing bundles, copying bundle files, etc, just remember that a bundle is nothing more than an assembly designed to work with MBuild.

Each bundle defines a set of rules that can be used in MBuild. To actually load them into the MBuild engine, you need to reference the bundle assembly. This is done inside the project declaration of a Buildfile, which defines global parameters for your project. This declaration should only appear in the toplevel Buildfile used to describe your project. It looks something like this:

using [ 
	Core.Xml
	Tools.DocbookPdf
]

project [
	name = "MyProject"
	version = "0.10.0.0"

	refs [
		Core.Xml = 0.0.3.1
		Tools.DocbookPdf = 1.0.7.1
	]
]

output.xml = XslProcess [ input.xml stylesheet.xsl ]

output.pdf = DocbookPdf [ output.xml ]

This tells MBuild to ask the GAC to load one bundle assembly called "MBuildDynamic.Core.Xml" with version 0.0.3.1, and another called "MBuildDynamic.Tools.DocbookPdf" with version 1.0.7.1. This exact versioning is not required (just leave off the "= w.x.y.z" bit), but it is strongly recommended. That way if someone else tries to build your software, you'll be sure that they're using the exact same build tools as you.

Now, this might seem a little scary to those of you who have experience with the GNU autotools, because it's always a pain in the ass to require the user to user exactly the same versions as you: automake 1.8 and libtool 1.5 and gettext 0.14. But MBuild can include the bundle files directly with your source distribution, and because of the platform provided by the .NET runtime, you can be guaranteed that they'll work correctly on everyone else's computer. (FIXME: feature not implemented! But don't worry, it's gonna be really easy to write, I swear.)

You might also wonder why it's necessary to first say that you're using the namespace Core.Xml and then also say that you're referencing the assembly Core.Xml. This confused me when I was first learning to program with C#. This two-stage setup is needed because any assembly can define types in any namespace; two different assemblies can even define types in one shared namespace. (For instance, the core assemblies corlib.dll and System.dll both define types in the System.Text namespace.) You can call an assembly anything you want; it's just (good) convention to name it the same thing as the topmost namespace it provides. But there's no reason that I can't create an assembly called "starfleet.dll" that declares types in the namespaces "Frontiers.Final" as well as "System.Xml". Note, then, that the "MBuildDynamic." prefix is applied in two cases: to the namespaces that are provided by a bundle, and to the names of the bundle assemblies.

Rules and Arguments

Consider this example:

myprogram.exe = CompileExe [ myreference.dll mysource.cs ]

As you might hope, this will cause MBuild to execute a command that looks something like this:

csc /out:myprogram.exe /target:exe /r:myreference.dll mysource.cs

Here's a question: how does MBuild know which dependency is the C# source file, and which one is a DLL reference? We've learned that the name of a target (and, hence, the name of a dependency) has no special meaning, and I'll tell you that the order of dependencies doesn't matter.

This is a remarkable property. You can just give MBuild a list of dependencies, and it will figure out what they mean. If "myprogram" depends on "libfoo.so", you must want to link to it. If it depends on "mysource.c", you must want to compile it. I think this is the most important feature in the whole MBuild system. You tell it a dependency, and it determines what information that dependency encodes. It determines the meaning of that dependency. No need to explicitly say "this is a source file" or "this is a library to link in". MBuild just does what you want.

The MBuild engine for determining the meaning of a dependency is basically a system for passing arguments to a function. The "function" is the rule being invoked. Internally, the rule sends the MBuild engine a list of arguments that it accepts. This list is just like the list of arguments to a regular old C function: they have names and types. Unlike the arguments to a C function, there's no particular order to them. The MBuild engine then evaluates the target's dependencies, replacing a dependency on some abstract target with a reference to some specific value. As noted before, each value has a type, and these types form a heirarchy similar to the rule name heirarchy. This heirarchy is used to match values to arguments -- each value is assigned to the rule argument that is its closest match in the heirarchy. This is the key -- the heirarchy of value types is very large; consequently, many fine shades of meaning can be determined by looking at a value's type. For instance, the Languages.CSharp bundle defines a value class for C# source files called CSSource. That class is a subclass of TextFile, which is a subclass of the MBFile file result class. (The "MB" is to avoid name clashes with the .NET framework's type System.IO.File. Similarly, the string result type is called MBString to avoid conflicts with System.String.)

Can this scheme really capture every nuance to the build system? Yes, if you add enough arguments to your rule function, and supply your target with enough dependencies. It sounds like this system could spiral into insane complexity, and with a naive implementation it very easily would. MBuild makes your life easier by letting arguments have default values, so that you don't need to specify them if the default is good enough. For instance, the CompileExe rule has a "csc" argument, which is a reference to the C# compiler to invoke. It would be a pain to have to add a dependency on "the_csharp_compiler" for every executable you compile, so the argument has a default value: it points to the probed system C# compiler. If you want to use a special compiler, you can override this value; but in the vast majority of use cases, you don't have to worry about it.

Consider an example from the toplevel Buildfile of MBuild itself. This rule is used to generate an MBuild bundle using a tool called mb-bundlegen. This tool uses a simple code processor to generate a lot of tedious boilerplate code, then compiles it into a .NET assembly. The target definition looks like this:

MBuildDynamic.Languages.CSharp.dll = BundlegenProcess [
	Languages.CSharp.bundle
	MBuildDynamic.Core.dll
	Mono.Build.dll
	mbuild.snk
	our_bundlegen
] 

Here's the detailed analyis:

Languages.CSharp.bundle evaluates to a value of type BundleSource, which is a source file for the mb-bundlegen tool. Meanwhile, the BundlegenProcess rule accepts an argument called "sources" of type BundleSource. The values assigned to this argument are passed on to the invocation of mb-bundlegen as the source files to compile. This is a perfect match, so the value of Languages.CSharp.bundle is assigned to the "sources" argument.

MBuildDynamic.Core.dll and Mono.Build.dll evaluate to type DllAssembly, so they are assigned to an argument called "refs". The assembly being compiled will be linked with them.

mbuild.snk evaluates to a value of type StrongnameKeypairFile, a crytographic key file used to digitally sign assembly files. It is assigned to the "snkfile" argument and will be used to digitally sign the output assembly.

our_bundlegen evaluates to type BinaryInfo, which is a generic Result class describing an executable program. So it is assigned to the "bundlegen" argument -- it is the program that will be invoked to do the processing.

MBuild supports optional arguments, which don't always have to be given a value. It also supports multiple-valued arguments, which can be given more than one value. For instance, the C# compilation rule, CSCompile, also supports an "snkfile" argument. However, it is marked as optional, because you don't need to digitally sign assemblies. If the argument is given a value, the assembly will be signed; if no value is given, it won't. No need for you to explicitly code the logic; MBuild just does what you want. (The "snkfile" argument for the BundlegenProcess rule is not optional, because an assembly must be signed in order to install it into the GAC, and all MBuild bundles are loaded from the GAC.)

Phew! That was long. Let's move on and start putting all this theory into practice.

Next: F-Spot Migration Case Study

A First Look at MBuild

Let's see some of the features that you get when working with MBuild. This walkthrough will assume that you have the MBuild source available; if you don't, it still ought to be somewhat useful.

Let's look at the file called "Buildfile," which is the MBuild equivalent of a Makefile. It defines what gets built in the toplevel directory.

using [ Core
        Core.Clr
        Core.Install
        Languages.CSharp
        Tools.Bundlegen
]

# information about this project

project [
        name = mbuild
        version = 0.0.3.1

        # Versioned assembly references pulled
        # from the GAC. No more aclocal hell!

        ref [
                Languages.CSharp = 0.0.3.1
                Tools.Jay = 0.0.3.1
                Tools.PkgConfig = 0.0.3.1
                Tools.Bundlegen = 0.0.3.1
                Tools.Monodoc = 0.0.3.1
        ]
]

# There are also Buildfiles in these
# subdirectories.

subdirs [
        doc
        scripts
        demo
        Monkeywrench/Monkeywrench
        mb-bundlegen
        api-docs
]

...

# Load a response file to get the list of sources
# Use a custom installer that installs the DLL into
# the GAC, not just libdir.
 
Mono.Build.dll = [@Mono.Build.dll.sources mbuild.snk]
         with [ install = /config/mbuild/gac_installer ]

...

MBuildDynamic.Tools.Monodoc.dll = BundlegenProcess [
        Tools.Monodoc.bundle
        MBuildDynamic.Core.dll
        Mono.Build.dll
        resources = api-docs/mkmstoc.xsl
        mbuild.snk
        our_bundlegen
] with [ install = /config/mbuild/gac_installer ]

Even if the exact details of how MBuild works aren't clear, I hope that the general idea of what's going on in MBuild comes through.

The Basics

The first time that you run MBuild for a project, you need to tell it where to find the source code. This is because MBuild has builtin support for out-of-place builds ("$srcdir != $builddir"), so the source code won't always be in same place that you run the build from. We're going to show off this feature:

mbuild$ mkdir BUILD
mbuild$ cd BUILD
BUILD$ mbuild -i ..
Initializing with source directory `..' and buildfiles called `Buildfile'
Building `/config/tools/pkgconfig/pkgconfig_name' ...
Building `/config/tools/pkgconfig/pkgconfig_binary' ...
Building `/config/tools/monodoc/monodoc_name' ...
Building `/config/tools/monodoc/monodoc_binary' ...
Building `/config/tools/monodoc/monodoc_program' ...
Building `/config/tools/jay/jay_name' ...
Building `/config/tools/jay/jay_binary' ...
Building `/mb-gtkconfig/glade-sharp-pclibs' ...
Building `/mb-gtkconfig/glade-sharp-pccheck' ...
Building `/config/clr/gacutil_names' ...
Building `/config/clr/gacutil_binary' ...
Building `/config/clr/gacutil_program' ...
Building `/config/clr/sn_names' ...
Building `/config/clr/sn_binary' ...
Building `/config/clr/sn_program' ...
Building `/config/tools/bundlegen/bundlegen_name' ...
Building `/config/tools/bundlegen/bundlegen_binary' ...
Built 17 targets, 4 did not need rebuilding (with dups).

The -i argument stands for "initialize", and the .. points to the source directory. If you just want to run your builds in-place, you can just run mbuild -i . from the source directory.

When you run MBuild with the -i argument, it merely runs some configuration checks; it doesn't execute a full build. To do that, just run the tool without any command-line arguments:

BUILD$ mbuild
Building `/mb-bundlegen/Mono.GetOptions.dll' ...
Building `/mb-bundlegen/AssemblyInfo.cs' ...
Building `/project/version' ...
Building `/mb-bundlegen/GeneratedAssemblyVersionInfo.cs' ...
Building `/mb-bundlegen/mb-bundlegen.cs' ...
Building `/mb-bundlegen/Tokenizer.cs' ...
Building `/mb-bundlegen/Parser.jay' ...
Building `/config/tools/jay/default_skeleton_dir' ...
Building `/config/tools/jay/default_skeleton_name' ...
Building `/config/tools/jay/default_skeleton' ...
Building `/config/tools/jay/default_flags' ...
Building `/mb-bundlegen/Parser.cs' ...
warning 3010: Jay printed warnings:
   /usr/bin/jay: 2 rules never reduced
   /usr/bin/jay: 6 shift/reduce conflicts.
Building `/config/generic/enable_debug' ...
Building `/config/lang/csharp/enable_debug' ...
Building `/config/lang/csharp/csc_names' ...
Building `/config/lang/csharp/csc' ...
Building `/mb-bundlegen/mb-bundlegen.exe' ...
...
Built 150 targets, 2045 did not need rebuilding (with dups).
1 warnings, 0 errors

One convenient thing about MBuild is that it doesn't use file modification times to detect changes:

BUILD$ touch ../mbuild/mbuild.cs
BUILD$ mbuild
[ Nothing is built ]

Cleaning

MBuild also has builtin support for "cleaning" built objects. The command-line argument -c puts MBuild in "clean mode". For instance, we can clean one file like this:

BUILD$ ls -l mbuild.exe
-rwxrwxr-x  1 peter peter 13312 Aug 13 15:00 mbuild.exe
BUILD$ mbuild -c mbuild.exe
Cleaned 1 targets
BUILD$ ls -l mbuild.exe
ls: mbuild.exe: No such file or directory

Of course, you don't have to clean files through MBuild. It will notice if you just delete a file from under it.

BUILD$ mbuild mbuild.exe
[ mbuild.exe is rebuilt ]
BUILD$ rm mbuild.exe
BUILD$ mbuild
/mbuild.exe: warning 3008: The cached external result for /mbuild.exe was not valid; rebuilding.
   $builddir/mbuild.exe
Building `/mbuild.exe' ...
Built 1 targets, 1826 did not need rebuilding (with dups).
1 warnings, 0 errors

We see that MBuild will complain if you do this, but it knows what to do in response.

MBuild is also aware of recursion. You can move into subdirectories and MBuild will run a build for the files in that subdirectory of sources. First, we clean all built objects by giving MBuild the -a flag. (There is a subtle difference between mbuild -c and mbuild -ca. More on that later.)

BUILD$ mbuild -ca
Cleaned 17 targets
BUILD$ cd mb-bundlegen
mb-bundlegen$ mbuild
Building `/mb-bundlegen/GeneratedAssemblyVersionInfo.cs' ...
Building `/mb-bundlegen/Parser.cs' ...
warning 3010: Jay printed warnings:
   /usr/bin/jay: 2 rules never reduced
   /usr/bin/jay: 6 shift/reduce conflicts.
Building `/mb-bundlegen/mb-bundlegen.exe' ...
Built 3 targets, 21 did not need rebuilding (with dups).
1 warnings, 0 errors

Unlike any other recursive make tool that I've seen, MBuild still knows about targets above the working directory. You can tell MBuild to look at them with the -g ("global") option. We'll also throw in the --debug-logs option, which gets MBuild to tell you what commands that it's running. It shows that MBuild is actually using relative paths with .. in them to get the build output in the right place.

mb-bundlegen$ mbuild -g --debug-logs
[ A lot of build output ]

Pretty cool, huh?

Operations and Tags

Now, the difference between the -a and the -g option is probably not immediately obvious. I'll try to work up to explaining what's going on there. The basic thing to know is that the MBuild command-line client has two inputs:

A list of targets to operate on.

The operation to perform on those targets.

"Operations" are basic build tasks; they'll make sense if you've used make before. In make, build operations are usually implemented with "pseudotargets", which don't actually correspond to a file: they're called all, clean, install, dist, etc. In MBuild, you specify the operation to execute separately from the targets to execute it on. (Or, if you prefer, think about it as activating a certain mode in the tool.) Instead of make clean, we specify a "clean" operation with mbuild -c. Instead of make install, we put the tool in install mode with mbuild -I. Instead of make dist, we have mbuild -d. And the default operation in mbuild is just to build targets, similar to make all.

Where does MBuild get its list of targets to operate on? There are four basic scopes that MBuild works inside:

By default, MBuild looks at all the targets in and below the current working directory.

The -g flag tells MBuild to look at targets globally, even ones that live above the current working directory.

The -l flag tells MBuild to look at targets locally, ignoring ones that that live below the current working directory.

The -b prefix option makes MBuild use the default here-and-below behavior, but as if you were working in the prefix you specify. Not terribly useful or important.

MBuild then prunes this list of targets by looking at tags. A tag is a piece of metadata attached to a target; it can be automatically defined by build rules, specified by the Buildfile author, or dynamically determined at build time. Tags have a name and a value; usually, the value is boolean. MBuild uses tags to filter its list of targets:

By default, MBuild only operates on targets that have a tag called default set to true. "Important" targets should have this flag set; turning it on is sort of like making your target a dependency of "make all" in make.

If you give MBuild the -a flag, it will operate on all targets, regardless of any flags.

You can also specify another tag to check for. The command mbuild +tagname will only operate on those targets that have a true boolean value for the tag tagname. For instance, in a well-designed build, mbuild +docs will only build documentation files. You can give more then one set of tags at once: mbuild +docs +config +default.

Or you can just give a target name to act on. Target names look like Unix path names but live in different namespace. A well-structured build system, however, will have a close correspondence between files and targets, so that mbuild mbuild.exe will operate on mbuild.exe. Again, you can specify more than one target name: mbuild mbuild.exe /config/install/prefix Monkeywrench/Monkeywrench/BuildfileParser.cs.

You see that this system is better than the "pseudotarget" route that Makefile authors are forced to go. Say you've just added a new major target to your make project -- an executable, a library, etc. You remember to add it to the dependencies of your all target, so that it gets build when you run make all. But often enough you forget to add it to the rule for install target, and then later realize that you forgot to add code for it in the clean target. Now, tools such as automake avoid many of these problems, but the MBuild approach is inherently more reliable. Once you add the default tag to your target, mbuild will automatically build it, mbuild -c will automatically clean it, and mbuild -I will automatically install it. Even better, you can actually run these operations in a limited scope: mbuild -I +docs will install only documentation, without any special support needed in the Buildfiles.

So, back to examples. One boring mode that I haven't mentioned is the --print-targets mode; it justs prints out the names of the targets that you've selected. Let's combine it with what we just learned.

mb-bundlegen$ cd ..
BUILD$ mbuild --print-targets
[ List of default targets is printed ]
BUILD$ mbuild --print-targets +default
[ The same list is printed ]
BUILD$ mbuild --print-targets +docs
[ A list of documentation targets is printed ]

We can also demonstrate the differences between the default, global, and local operation scopes:

BUILD$ cd api-docs
api-docs$ mbuild --print-targets -a
[ A long list of files is printed ]
api-docs$ mbuild --print-targets -a -l
[ A much shorter list is printer ]
api-docs$ mbuild --print-targets -a -g
[ A very long list is printed ]

Showing Target Values

In MBuild, targets are more than just files -- they are entries in a namespace that have values associated with them. (A fuller explanation is forthcoming in the next section.) You can get MBuild to show these values with the "show" operation, activated with the -s option:

api-docs$ cd ..
BUILD$ mbuild -s
/mb-bundlegen/mb-bundlegen.exe = $builddir/mb-bundlegen/mb-bundlegen.exe
/MBuildDynamic.Tools.PkgConfig.dll = $builddir/MBuildDynamic.Tools.PkgConfig.dll
/MBuildDynamic.Tools.Monodoc.dll = $builddir/MBuildDynamic.Tools.Monodoc.dll
/Mono.Build.dll = $builddir/Mono.Build.dll
/MBuildDynamic.Tools.Bundlegen.dll = $builddir/MBuildDynamic.Tools.Bundlegen.dll
/mbuild.exe = $builddir/mbuild.exe
/MBuildDynamic.Languages.CSharp.dll = $builddir/MBuildDynamic.Languages.CSharp.dll
/MBuildDynamic.Tools.Jay.dll = $builddir/MBuildDynamic.Tools.Jay.dll
/Monkeywrench.dll = $builddir/Monkeywrench.dll
/MBuildDynamic.Core.dll = $builddir/MBuildDynamic.Core.dll
/mb-gtkconfig/mb-gtkconfig.exe = $builddir/mb-gtkconfig/mb-gtkconfig.exe
/mb-gtkconfig/glade-sharp-pclibs = "-r:/usr/lib/mono/gtk-sharp/glade-sharp.dll ..."
/mb-gtkconfig/glade-sharp-pccheck = True
/scripts/mb-gtkconfig = $srcdir/scripts/mb-gtkconfig
/scripts/mb-bundlegen = $srcdir/scripts/mb-bundlegen
/scripts/mbuild = $srcdir/scripts/mbuild

You can see that this mode is similar to the --print-targets mode, but each target's value is also evaluated and printed. In this case, almost all of the default targets have file values, so their values look like filenames as well. But note that glade-sharp-pclibs is a string. We can also see the values of, say, configuration items in MBuild. Configuration targets are labeled with the tag config, so we can see their values with the following commands:

BUILD$ mbuild -s +config
Building `/config/generic/build_tests' ...
/config/generic/build_tests = True
Building `/config/generic/enable_optimize' ...
/config/generic/enable_optimize = True
Building `/config/generic/build_docs' ...
/config/generic/build_docs = True
/config/generic/enable_debug = True
Building `/config/generic/build_examples' ...
/config/generic/build_examples = True
Building `/config/install/default_prefix' ...
Building `/config/install/prefix' ...
/config/install/prefix = "/usr/local"
Building `/config/mbuild/good_example' ...
/config/mbuild/good_example = True
/config/lang/csharp/enable_debug = True
/config/tools/bundlegen/enable_debug = True
Built 7 targets, 5 did not need rebuilding (with dups).
BUILD$ ls config
ls: config: No such file or directory

The ls command is supposed to emphasize that these configuration targets exist in MBuild's namespace, but not on the filesystem.

Configuration

The MBuild command-line client will use the config tag get a list of targets that represent configuration options. You can then change their values in the "config" mode (-C). By default, the config mode acts on only targets with the config tag, but you can change that if you want. In general, however, the MBuild equivalent of ./configure is mbuild -C:

BUILD$ mbuild -C
Build tests by default? (y/n, default: y)
[ hit enter ]
(Didn't understand; going with the default.)
Enable optimization options? (y/n, default: y)
[ hit enter ]
(Didn't understand; going with the default.)
Build documentation by default? (y/n, default: y)
[ hit enter ]
(Didn't understand; going with the default.)
Enable debugging options? (y/n, default: y)
[ hit enter ]
(Didn't understand; going with the default.)
Build examples by default? (y/n, default: y)
[ hit enter ]
(Didn't understand; going with the default.)
Specify the prefix of directories that files will be installed into (default: /usr/local)
[ enter /tmp/mbuild-install ]
This is an example configuration option. Ok? (y/n, default: y)
[ enter n ]
Compile C# programs with debugging symbols? (y/n, default: y)
[ hit enter ]
(Didn't understand; going with the default.)
Generate debugging information for MBuild bundles? (y/n, default: y)
[ hit enter ]
(Didn't understand; going with the default.)
Built 1 targets, 11 did not need rebuilding (with dups).
BUILD$ mbuild -s +config
/config/generic/build_tests = True
/config/generic/enable_optimize = True
/config/generic/build_docs = True
/config/generic/enable_debug = True
/config/generic/build_examples = True
/config/install/prefix = "/tmp/mbuild-install"
/config/mbuild/good_example = False
/config/lang/csharp/enable_debug = True
/config/tools/bundlegen/enable_debug = True

We set up a bunch of generic configuration options, and few that were actually relevant to MBuild. Obviously, the interface for configuring is kind of lame at the moment. There is a prototype graphical configurator called mb-gtkconfig.exe, which is built in the mb-gtkconfig/ directory of the MBuild source. It seems to work, but it's not been very well tested so far.

The configuration prompts are derived from another tag on the configuration targets called, sensibly, prompt. See Buildfile.config for an example:

BUILD$ cat ../Buildfile.config
using [
        Core.Config
        Core.Clr
        Core.Install
        Tools.PkgConfig
]

...

good_example = ConfigBool[true] with [
        prompt = "This is an example configuration option. Ok?"
]
...

Installation

Now that we've changed the install prefix into something unprivileged, we can run an install.

BUILD$ mbuild -I
Installing ...
Building `/config/install/prefix_dir' ...
Building `/config/install/bindir' ...
Building `/config/install/bindir_installer' ...
 + /mb-bundlegen/mb-bundlegen.exe
Building `/config/install/libdir' ...
Building `/config/mbuild/gac_installer' ...
 + /MBuildDynamic.Tools.PkgConfig.dll
 + /MBuildDynamic.Tools.Monodoc.dll
 + /Mono.Build.dll
 + /MBuildDynamic.Tools.Bundlegen.dll
 + /mbuild.exe
 + /MBuildDynamic.Languages.CSharp.dll
 + /MBuildDynamic.Tools.Jay.dll
Building `/config/install/libdir_installer' ...
 + /Monkeywrench.dll
 + /MBuildDynamic.Core.dll
 + /scripts/mb-gtkconfig
 + /scripts/mb-bundlegen
 + /scripts/mbuild
Built 9 targets, 2071 did not need rebuilding (with dups).
Installed 13 targets

What are these "installer" targets that are getting built? Well, MBuild's method for installation is clever -- probably too clever for its own good, but that's another story. MBuild figures out which targets to install by looking at a tag called install (surprise, amazement). However, this tag is not just a boolean value. It points to a special kind of target called an installer. An installer is a built object that contains code to run an installation routine. That routine is passed the value of the target possessing the install tag, and it does whatever makes sense with that target. Usually, this is just a file copy, as we can see by looking at some of these installer targets:

BUILD$ mbuild -s /config/install/bindir_installer
/config/install/bindir_installer = [copy to /tmp/mbuild-install/bin]
BUILD$ mbuild -s /config/mbuild/gac_installer
/config/mbuild/gac_installer = [install into gac, root = /tmp/mbuild-install/lib, 
program = { GacutilProgram::Program = [program: gacutil ] }, package = mbuild]

These installer targets also implement uninstallation, so MBuild should support perfectly that least-tested operation, make uninstall. The MBuild option to activate this mode is --uninstall:

BUILD$ mbuild --uninstall
Unnstalling ...
 + /mb-bundlegen/mb-bundlegen.exe
 + /MBuildDynamic.Tools.PkgConfig.dll
 + /MBuildDynamic.Tools.Monodoc.dll
 + /Mono.Build.dll
 + /MBuildDynamic.Tools.Bundlegen.dll
 + /mbuild.exe
 + /MBuildDynamic.Languages.CSharp.dll
 + /MBuildDynamic.Tools.Jay.dll
 + /Monkeywrench.dll
 + /MBuildDynamic.Core.dll
 + /scripts/mb-gtkconfig
 + /scripts/mb-bundlegen
 + /scripts/mbuild
Uninstalled 13 targets
BUILD$ find /tmp/mbuild-install -type f
[ Nothing. ]

As you might guess from the presence of /tmp/mbuild-install in the value of bindir_installer, the latter has a dependency on the former:

BUILD$ mbuild -C /config/install/prefix
Specify the prefix of directories that files will be installed into (default: /tmp/mbuild-install)
[ enter /tmp/mbuild-install2 ]
BUILD$ mbuild -s /config/install/bindir_installer
Building `/config/install/prefix_dir' ...
Building `/config/install/bindir' ...
Building `/config/install/bindir_installer' ...
/config/install/bindir_installer = [copy to /tmp/mbuild-install2/bin]
Built 3 targets, 2 did not need rebuilding (with dups).

We see that bindir_installer needs to be rebuilt after we change the value of /config/install/prefix.

Distribution

Finally, MBuild can also copy files into a directory for distribution. It won't actually tar that directory up, but baby steps, baby steps...

BUILD$ mbuild -d
Distributing to `mbuild-0.0.3.1' ...
 + /Monkeywrench/Monkeywrench/OperationFunc.cs
 + /Monkeywrench/Monkeywrench/ProviderBuilder.cs
 + /Monkeywrench/Monkeywrench/ITargetRequestSink.cs
Building `/Monkeywrench/Monkeywrench/.monkeywrench_resource_0' ...
 + /Monkeywrench/Monkeywrench/.monkeywrench_resource_0
 + /Monkeywrench/Monkeywrench/BuildfileProvider.cs
...
Building `/project/compat-code' ...
 + /scripts/mb-gtkconfig
 + /scripts/mb-bundlegen
 + /scripts/mbuild
Building `/scripts/.monkeywrench_resource_0' ...
 + /scripts/.monkeywrench_resource_0
Built 171 targets, 2830 did not need rebuilding (with dups).
Copied 263 targets for distribution
2 warnings, 0 errors

A distribution should include all components of the source tree, so you will see that MBuild builds some various targets that haven't been built before. The .monkeywrench_resource_ targets, for example, are targets pointing to Buildfiles and source listing files. Anyway, if you've ever tried to get make dist working, you know how much of a pain it can be. Look through the MBuild Buildfiles and try and find any code needed to get distribution working. None.

Well, that's a quick tour of the frontend of MBuild. Now, let's see how it all works under the hood...

Next: The MBuild Architecture

F-Spot Migration Case Study

If you're interested in using MBuild for one of your projects, you're probably curious about how one transitions from a build system based on autoconf and automake to one based on MBuild. This section will go through a detailed example involving the popular photo management application F-Spot. Like many of the applications at which MBuild is aimed, the F-Spot build involves C# libraries, C# executables, C libraries, and miscellaneous support files that help F-Spot integrate with the GNOME desktop environment. This makes it a good candidate for an MBuild migration case study.

Of course, when I say "migrate to MBuild", that doesn't mean that one has to stop using the autotools. MBuild Buildfiles can coexist with autotools files -- namely, configure.in and Makefile.am -- without problems. In fact, as I will describe below, it is important to reference the preexisting build system while writing new MBuild files so that unexpected changes don't cause unforseen difficulties for developers, packagers, and users.

General Migration Approach

I'll start off by describing the general approach to writing Buildfiles for an autoconf- and automake-based project. The task is generally one of drudgery, not creativity, since all build tools are basically expressing similar ideas in different languages. It is especially straightforward when translating from the autotools because there is essentially a one-to-one correspondence between Makefile.ams and Buildfiles. The only twist is that the commands in configure.in also need to be translated into the MBuild model, since MBuild incorporates the functionality of autoconf. It's best to start by translating configure.in since it is lowest in the dependency stack, in a way: "normal" targets will rely on the values of configuration targets, but not the other way around. The configure.in file also contains the project-wide information (e.g., package name and version) that goes in the toplevel Buildfile.

Once the configury has been translated, one can just create a Buildfile in every directory in which there is a Makefile.am and translate targets one-by-one. All this task requires is patience, a good understanding of automake idioms, and a knowledge of the library of bundles that come with MBuild. Presuming that most people do not have the latter, I'll describe the F-Spot migration in detail in the next section, showing the recommended ways to do pkg-config checks, build C libraries, compile C#, perform autoconf-style substitutions, and do other tasks that are commonplace in Linux builds.

Once translation has been completed, it is important to check one's results. There are two key areas that need verification: the result of installing the built package, and the contents of a generated source distribution. In both cases, MBuild has a few rough edges that mean that identical installations and distributions are unlikely to be obtained, but the directories and major files involved should agree. One way to compare installation results is to perform a make install with DESTDIR set to some temporary directory. Running find DESTDIR -print will then produce a listing of all the file installed (except in some rare cases where files are installed with special code that is buggy and doesn't know about DESTDIR). Running mbuild --describe-install will produce a similar listing of operations, and the two lists can be compared. Comparing distributions is easy, although of course a distribution created with mbuild -d won't include files like config.sub, configure.in, and so on.

Of course, if one finds oneself moving to building a package solely with MBuild, it might be reasonable to polish the initial Buildfiles into what might be called "idiomatic MBuild." At that point it might make sense to rename installation directories, for instance to take advantage of the "compatibility code" concept that MBuild uses. But such polish is beyond the scope of this page.

Here's a shortened version of the above advice, with some more pointers thrown that will be explained in the following section:

Create a toplevel Buildfile and transcribe the basic project information from configure.in.
Convert the checks from configure.in into MBuild targets in the toplevel Buildfile.
If necessary, create comments in subdirectory Buildfiles reminding yourself of files created with AC_CONFIG_FILES or AC_OUTPUT or of the contents of ALL_LINGUAS.
Transcribe any targets defined in the toplevel Makefile.am into the toplevel Buildfile.
Create Buildfiles in the subdirectories listed in SUBDIRS, in that order, and transcribe them from their corresponding Makefile.ams. Proceed recursively.
If you feel like it, put any common constructions, such as shared installation directories or system library references, in the toplevel Buildfile, and eliminate the redundant targets.
Once all the transcription seems to be done, compare the results of a make install with those of a mbuild -I or mbuild --describe-install. Make sure that you can run the results of an MBuild-based installation with all other files removed from your system.
Once those agree, compare the results of a make dist with those of a mbuild -d. Make sure that you can build from a bare distribution.

F-Spot: The Gory Details

We'll get started by translating configure.in for the reasons mentioned in the previous section. We start by opening a blank toplevel Buildfile in an editor and looking at configure.in in another window. The first few lines are:

AC_INIT(src/main.cs)

...

AM_INIT_AUTOMAKE(f-spot, 0.1.11)

AM_MAINTAINER_MODE

...

AC_PROG_CC
AC_ISC_POSIX
AC_HEADER_STDC
AM_PROG_LIBTOOL

The AC_INIT line is, as you might guess, essentially boilerplate. (The "src/main.cs" argument gives autoconf a tool for guessing where the source directory is; in MBuild, the user must specify it explicitly.) The AM_INIT_AUTOMAKE line gives us the official package name and version. The other macros are basically boilerplate and tell us what we already know: we're going to need to compile C shared libraries. From these lines we can write the beginnings of our toplevel Buildfile:

using [
	# Almost always want to include this
        Core 

	# Will add more namespaces as needed by the toplevel
	# rules
]

project [
        name = f-spot
        version = 0.1.11

	# F-Spot doesn't version its install directories,
	# so this doesn't really matter, but the recommended
	# compatibility code would be something like this

        compat-code = 0.1

        ref [
                Languages.CSharp = 0.0.4.0
		# MBuild's C compilation support is still tentative,
		# so we reflect that in the name of the bundle.
                Languages.CrappyC = 0.0.4.0

		# Will add more as needed in the project
        ]
]

subdirs [
	# We'll fill in the subdirectories here from
	# the SUBDIRS list in Makefile.am
]

Now there are a few more preamble lines that tell us about the bundles that we'll need to use:

AM_CONFIG_HEADER(config.h)

...

AC_PROG_INTLTOOL([0.21])

The AM_CONFIG_HEADER line tells us that the C code in F-Spot will expect a standard config.h file. MBuild comes with a bundle that can create an autoheader-style config.h called Frameworks.AutoheaderCompat, so we should add a reference to that in the project section. Similarly, MBuild supports intltool with the Frameworks.Intltool bundle. This latter bundle is a little unusual because it actually includes the files from the intltool package. Because of this, the version of the Frameworks.Intltool bundle tracks the version of intltool that it bundles. Our project section now looks like:

project [
        name = f-spot
        version = 0.1.11
        compat-code = 0.1

        ref [
                Languages.CSharp = 0.0.4.0
                Languages.CrappyC = 0.0.4.0
                Frameworks.Gettext = 0.0.4.0 # required by intltool.
                Frameworks.Intltool = 0.34.2.0
                Frameworks.AutoheaderCompat = 0.0.4.0
        ]
]

Now we get to the actual prerequisite checks in the configure.in file:

AC_PATH_PROG(MONO, mono)
AC_PATH_PROG(MCS, mcs)

MBuild finds these programs automatically, so we don't need to do anything about these lines.

AC_MSG_CHECKING([for mono.pc])
if test -z `$PKG_CONFIG --variable=prefix mono`; then
  AC_MSG_ERROR([missing the mono.pc file, usually found in the mono-devel package])
else
  AC_MSG_RESULT([found])
fi

This is a check to see if the Mono development files are installed. MBuild comes with a bundle that supports common pkg-config options called Tools.PkgConfig. First, we reference the bundle in the project section and use it in the using section. Then a simple prerequisite that a certain pkg-config module be installed can be expressed in the Buildfile as:

mono-pclibs = [ "mono" ]

The Tools.PkgConfig bundle includes a rule that matches any target name ending in "-pclibs" to the PkgConfigLibs rule, which calls pkg-config --libs with the specified packages and returns an error if the packages aren't installed. The target is also automatically decorated with the prereq tag, so that the libraries will be checked for whenever a new build directory is initialized.

needed_dlls="Mono.Data.SqliteClient Mono.Posix System.Runtime.Remoting System.Web System.Web.Services"
for i in $needed_dlls; do
  AC_MSG_CHECKING([for $i.dll])
  if test ! -e `$PKG_CONFIG --variable=prefix mono`/lib/mono/1.0/$i.dll; then
    AC_MSG_ERROR([missing required mono DLL: $i.dll])
  else
    AC_MSG_RESULT([found])
  fi
done

This code checks and sees if certain C# libraries are available. The MBuild C# bundle includes a rule that will automatically check for referenced DLLs, so we could ignore these checks and just reference the desired DLLs in thet appropriate places. But it never hurts to centralize things, and we can invoke the DLL check rules explicitly:

Mono.Data.SqliteClient.dll = CSharpSystemDllCheck []
Mono.Posix.dll = CSharpSystemDllCheck []
Mono.Security.dll = CSharpSystemDllCheck []
System.Runtime.Remoting.dll = CSharpSystemDllCheck []
System.Web.dll = CSharpSystemDllCheck []
System.Web.Services.dll = CSharpSystemDllCheck []
ICSharpCode.SharpZipLib.dll = CSharpSystemDllCheck []

For consistency with the existing checks, we've also added checks for a few DLLs referenced by f-spot.exe that doxn't appear in configure.in. The next chunk of configury code is:

LIBGNOME_REQUIRED=2.2
LIBGNOMEUI_REQUIRED=2.2
LIBEXIF_REQUIRED_MIN=0.5.7
LIBEXIF_REQUIRED_MAX=0.7.0
GTKSHARP_REQUIRED=2.7
MONO_REQUIRED=1.1.7
GTK_REQUIRED=2.6
DBUS_SHARP=0.23

dnl -- this check is
LCMS_REQUIRED=1.12
dnl -- LIBGPHOTO2_REQUIRED=2.1.4

PKG_CHECK_MODULES(F, libgnome-2.0 >= $LIBGNOME_REQUIRED libgnomeui-2.0 >= $LIBGNOMEUI_REQUIRED \
 libexif >= $LIBEXIF_REQUIRED_MIN libexif < $LIBEXIF_REQUIRED_MAX gtkhtml-sharp-2.0 >= \
 $GTKSHARP_REQUIRED gconf-sharp-2.0 >= $GTKSHARP_REQUIRED glade-sharp-2.0 >= $GTKSHARP_REQUIRED \
 gnome-vfs-sharp-2.0 >= $GTKSHARP_REQUIRED gtk+-2.0 >= $GTK_REQUIRED \
 mono >= $MONO_REQUIRED dbus-sharp >= $DBUS_SHARP)
AC_SUBST(F_CFLAGS)
AC_SUBST(F_LIBS)

This code checks for the bulk of the libraries required by F-Spot. The MBuild form for checking for them is a logical extension of the Mono case earlier:

fspot-pclibs = [
        "gtkhtml-sharp-2.0 >= 2.7"
        "gconf-sharp-2.0 >= 2.7"
        "glade-sharp-2.0 >= 2.7"
        "gnome-vfs-sharp-2.0 >= 2.7"
        "dbus-sharp >= 0.23"
]

fspot-pcflags = [
        "libgnome-2.0 >= 2.2"
        "libgnomeui-2.0 >= 2.2"
        "libexif >= 0.5.7"
        "libexif <= 0.7.0"
        "gtk+-2.0 >= 2.6"
]

misc-prereq-pclibs = [ "mono >= 1.1.7" ]

The F-Spot configure.in checks for all these items in one lump using the PKG_CHECK_MODULES macro. We do not do this for a good reason: the pkg-config call includes both C and C# modules, resulting in a strange set of values in the CFLAGS variable if the two kinds are lumped together. (For example, it contains flags such as -I:/usr/lib/pkgconfig/../../share/gapi-2.0/gnome-api.xml.) Fortunately, the only pkg-config information needed for C libraries is CFLAGS, while the only information needed for C# libaries is LIBS, so the two kinds of libraries can be separated easily without redundancy. (The fact that this is possible is not obvious a priori; I was only able to make the separation after writing Buildfile code for all the targets in the build.)

AC_PATH_PROG(GCONFTOOL, gconftool-2, no)
AM_GCONF_SOURCE_2

GConf is not currently used in F-Spot, so we ignore this bit. (As you might guess, I haven't implemented a GConf bundle yet.)

AC_CHECK_LIB(jpeg, jpeg_start_decompress, [],
             [AC_MSG_ERROR([libjpeg not found])], -lm)
AC_CHECK_HEADER(jpeglib.h, , [AC_MSG_ERROR([libjpeg not found])])
LIBJPEG='-ljpeg'

This is a classic pair of checks for a C library and its header files. The Languages.CrappyC bundle includes a rule that performs these checks:

libjpeg.so = CLibraryDevelCheck [
        "jpeglib.h"
        { "stdio.h", "stdlib.h" }
        func = "jpeg_start_decompress"
]

Here the name of the library to check for is guessed from the name of the target ("libjpeg.so") and the name of a header and a function to look for are given. The list of "stdio.h" and "stdlib.h" gives headers that are included before "jpeglib.h" itself is. At the moment, the MBuild rule doesn't allow for specifying other libraries to link to, unlike the equivalent configure check with its "-lm" argument. This will be added at some point, but we can often get away without it on Linux systems.

PKG_CHECK_MODULES(SQLITE, sqlite, have_sqlite2="yes", have_sqlite2="no")
PKG_CHECK_MODULES(SQLITE, sqlite3, have_sqlite3="yes", have_sqlite3="no")

if test "x$have_sqlite2" = "xno" -a "x$have_sqlite3" = "xno"; then
        AC_MSG_ERROR([You need to install either sqlite2 or sqlite3])
fi

This configure check is fairly self-explanatory. So is the analogous MBuild code:

sqlite2-pcprobe = [ "sqlite" ]
sqlite3-pcprobe = [ "sqlite3" ]

have-sqlite = sqlite2-pcprobe || sqlite3-pcprobe

assert-sqlite = Assert [ have-sqlite ] with [
        errnote = "You need the pkg-config development files for sqlite version 2 or sqlite version 3 to be installed."
]

A target with a "-pcprobe" suffix checks for a pkg-config package, but doesn't signal an error if the package isn't installed. Then the target "have-sqlite" is defined to be the logical "or" of the two pkg-config checks. (Note how much nicer it is to do this logic with genuine boolean values, instead of semi-portable shell script.) Finally, "assert-sqlite" is built with a special rule that signals an error if its argument is not true. Once again, the target is automatically decorated with the prereq tag so that it is checked upon initialization of the build directory. The errnote tag gives a more informative error message that is displayed if the assertion is failed. (FIXME: that bit is not implemented.)

PKG_CHECK_MODULES(LCMS, lcms >= $LCMS_REQUIRED, [],
        [AC_CHECK_LIB(lcms, cmsCreateBCHSWabstractProfile, [],
                     [AC_MSG_ERROR([liblcms not found])], -lm)
        AC_CHECK_HEADER(lcms.h, , [AC_MSG_ERROR([liblcms not found])])
        LCMS_LIBS='-llcms'
        LCMS_CFLAGS=''])

This mess checks if we have the LCMS library using both pkg-config and a plain check for the library and header. We can use the same rules that we've used before:

lcms-pcflags = [ "lcms >= 1.12" ]

liblcms.so = CLibraryDevelCheck [
        "lcms.h"
        { "stdio.h", "stdlib.h" }
        func = "cmsCreateBCHSWabstractProfile"
]

We skip over a plain pkg-config check for libgphoto2. Then we find:

LIBEXIF_API_CHANGE=0.6.0
PKG_CHECK_MODULES(LIBEXIF_API_CHECK, libexif >= $LIBEXIF_API_CHANGE, have_old_libexif=no, have_old_libexif=yes)

if test "x$have_old_libexif" = "xyes"; then
        EXIF_SOVERSION=9
else
        PKG_CHECK_MODULES(LIBEXIF_VERSION_CHECK, libexif >= 0.6.12, EXIF_SOVERSION=12, EXIF_SOVERSION=10)
fi
AC_SUBST(EXIF_SOVERSION)

Depending on the version of libexif installed, the value of EXIF_SOVERSION is set to track the version of the shared library installed. We can implement this in MBuild with more pkg-config probes and a rule for conditional-type expressions:

oldapi-exif-pcprobe = [ "libexif < 0.6.0" ]

newapi-exif-pcprobe = [ "libexif >= 0.6.12" ]

exif-soversion = Switch [
        cases = { oldapi-exif-pcprobe, newapi-exif-pcprobe, true }
        { "9", "12", "10" }
]

The first two targets are self-explanatory. The Switch rule is a builtin rule that can be used to emulate if-else expressions. It takes two arguments: a list of booleans, a list of results. Both lists are marked as "ordered", which means that the order of the arguments to the lists matters and is preserved inside MBuild. (This is why the lists are in braces and separated by commas.) The Switch rule walks down the list of booleans until it finds one that is true; it then returns the result in the corresponding position of the other list. In this case, the literal true value at the end of the list allows a default case to be specified. So the pseudocode equivalent of the above target is:

exif-soversion = {
	if oldapi-exif-pcprobe:
		return "9";
	else if newpi-exif-pcprobe:
		return "12";
	else
		return "10";
}

This rule may seem gross as things stand, but I'd like to point out that with a little syntactic sugar it would seem completely natural and reasonable.

AC_ARG_WITH(gnome-screensaver,[ --with-gnome-screensaver=PREFIX  set gnome gnome-screensaver prefix])

if test "x$with_gnome_screensaver" != "x"; then
        gnome_screensaver_prefix=$with_gnome_screensaver
else
        gnome_screensaver_prefix=$prefix
fi

if test -d $gnome_screensaver_prefix/lib/gnome-screensaver; then
        GNOME_SCREENSAVER_SAVERDIR=$gnome_screensaver_prefix/lib/gnome-screensaver/gnome-screensaver
else
        GNOME_SCREENSAVER_SAVERDIR=$gnome_screensaver_prefix/libexec/gnome-screensaver
fi

GNOME_SCREENSAVER_THEMESDIR=$gnome_screensaver_prefix/share/gnome-screensaver/themes

AC_SUBST(GNOME_SCREENSAVER_SAVERDIR)
AC_SUBST(GNOME_SCREENSAVER_THEMESDIR)

This bunch of code configures some paths related to gnome-screensaver. The equivalent MBuild syntax is (currently) a little verbose, but roughly analogous:

gnome-screensaver-prefix = Clone [ /config/install/prefix_dir ] with [
        config = true
        prompt = "The prefix in which the files for gnome-screensaver are installed"
]

gnome-screensaver-themedir = MakeInstallSubdirectory [
        gnome-screensaver-prefix
        "share/gnome-screensaver/themes"
]

lib-gss-dir = MakeInstallSubdirectory [
        gnome-screensaver-prefix "lib/gnome-screensaver/gnome-screensaver"
]

libexec-gss-dir = MakeInstallSubdirectory [
        gnome-screensaver-prefix "libexec/gnome-screensaver"
]

have-lib-gss-dir = ProbeInstallDirectory [ lib-gss-dir ]

gnome-screensaver-saverdir = Switch [
        cases = { have-lib-gss-dir, true }
        { lib-gss-dir, libexec-gss-dir }
]

Here, the differences between the autoconf and MBuild configuration systems become apparent. Instead of defining a flag that the configure script takes, we define a regular target and mark it with the config tag, indicating that the user might want to manually set its value. (This can be done with mbuild -C or with mb-gtkconfig.) The default value of the argument is made explicit and the relation between the configured variable and the rest of the build is much clearer in MBuild than it is with autoconf (in my opinion, of course). The MakeInstallSubdirectory rules just take a given directory and appends a string to it. (For somewhat arcane reasons, MBuild has an InstallDirectory type that is a subclass of MBString rather than MBDirectory, so it requires its own set of rules to manipulate.) The ProbeInstallDirectory returns a boolean indicating whether the specified directory exists. (This rule feels like something of a hack, but will probably be needed in many situations in which distributions disagree about where to install certain files, as is the case here.)

After skipping some more unused checks, we find:

ALL_LINGUAS="bg ca cs da de el ... sv th vi zh_CN zh_TW"

GETTEXT_PACKAGE=f-spot
AC_SUBST(GETTEXT_PACKAGE)
AC_DEFINE_UNQUOTED(GETTEXT_PACKAGE,"$GETTEXT_PACKAGE", [Gettext package])
AM_GLIB_GNU_GETTEXT

This is the usual gettext configuration. Because you can put configuration-type rules anywhere in an MBuild project, we'll move this stuff into the Buildfile inside the po subdirectory. The only information we really need to propagate is the list of languages, which we can paste into po/Buildfile in a temporary comment.

AC_SUBST(LIBJPEG)
AC_SUBST(LCMS_LIBS)
AC_SUBST(LCMS_CFLAGS)
AC_SUBST(CFLAGS)
AC_SUBST(CPPFLAGS)
AC_SUBST(LDFLAGS)

Don't need these in MBuild -- these are just artifacts of the separation of configuration and the rest of the build that one finds in the autotools.

expanded_libdir=`( case $prefix in NONE) prefix=$ac_default_prefix ;; *) ;; esac
                   case $exec_prefix in NONE) exec_prefix=$prefix ;; *) ;; esac
                   eval echo $libdir )`
AC_SUBST(expanded_libdir)

Nor do we need this. People who try to use autoconf variables like $libdir quickly find out that there is a bizarre system in which the variables refer to other variables and may be set to NONE as a default. MBuild can do proper dependencies on string variables and hence has no need for painful code like that seen above.

AC_CONFIG_FILES([src/f-spot],[chmod +x src/f-spot])

This is telling us that src/f-spot is created from src/f-spot.in. MBuild has builtin support for substitutions using the Core.Subst namespace, so implementation is not a problem. Again, because we are much more flexible than the autotools in where we do things, we will just put a comment in a newly-created src/Buildfile reminding ourselves to add code to create the f-spot wrapper script.

GNOME_ICON_THEME_PREFIX=`$PKG_CONFIG --variable=prefix gnome-icon-theme`
AC_SUBST(GNOME_ICON_THEME_PREFIX)

Once again the Tools.PkgConfig bundle gives us what we need compactly:

gnome-icon-theme-prefix = PkgConfigVar [ 
	"gnome-icon-theme" 
	variable = "prefix"
]

Finally, the traditional AC_OUTPUT at the end of the file:

AC_OUTPUT([
Makefile
FlickrNet/Makefile
icons/Makefile
libeog/Makefile
libeog/cursors/Makefile
libjpegtran/Makefile
libfspot/Makefile
libgphoto2-sharp/Makefile
semweb/Makefile
tools/Makefile
po/Makefile.in
src/Defines.cs
src/f-spot.exe.config
src/Makefile
f-spot.spec
f-spot.desktop.in
])

We can of course ignore all the Makefile outputs. We should create reminders in the appropriate Buildfiles for the other created files though: src/Defines.cs, src/f-spot.exe.config, f-spot.spec, and f-spot.desktop.in. We can implement these latter two targets right away using the aforementioned Core.Subst rules:

versubst = { VERSION = /project/version }

f-spot.desktop.in = Subst [
	f-spot.desktop.in.in
	versubst
]

f-spot.spec = Subst [
	f-spot.spec.in
	versubst
]

The target versubst is a dictionary that maps strings (VERSION in this configuration) to results (the value of the target /project/version here). The Subst rule takes such a dictionary as input and performs substitutions in the standard autoconf style, replacing @VERSION@ with the string value of the /project/version target.

At this point, we've finished going through configure.in. We can check to see that everything is good so far by seeing if MBuild is happy with our Buildfile so far:

f-spot$ mkdir BUILD
f-spot$ cd BUILD
BUILD$ mbuild -i ..
[Hopefully no errors]

Once everything checks out, we can now start the second step of MBuild migration: translating the Makefile.ams. Starting at the toplevel, we see:

SUBDIRS =               \
        FlickrNet       \
        icons           \
        libeog          \
        libjpegtran     \
        libfspot        \
        libgphoto2-sharp \
        semweb          \
        tools           \
        po              \
        src

This maps directly on to the subdirs [] section of the toplevel Buildfile. One thing to recall is that the order of the subdirectories matters to automake, because it can't handle dependencies between targets in different directories. MBuild has no problem with such dependencies, so after the migration is complete we might as well alphabetize the list. But it still makes sense to translate files in approximate dependency order, so for now we do this:

subdirs [
	# Uncomment each subdirectory after we write its Buildfile
	# and then rerun mbuild to check that our new file is
	# valid

        #FlickrNet
        #icons
        #libeog
        #libjpegtran
        #libfspot
        #libgphoto2-sharp
        #semweb
        #tools
        #po
        #src
]

The next group of commands in the Makefile.am after the SUBDIRS definition is:

desktop_in_files=       \
        f-spot.desktop.in       \
        f-spot-view.desktop.in

desktop_files=$(desktop_in_files:.desktop.in=.desktop)
@INTLTOOL_DESKTOP_RULE@

Applicationsdir = $(datadir)/applications
Applications_DATA = $(desktop_files)

This group of commands defines two XDG desktop files that should have translations merged from template files. (The fact that automake can't have its suite of canned rules extended is the reason that this ugly code is needed.) These files should then be installed in $(datadir)/applications. The equivalent code in MBuild takes advantage of the matchers in the Frameworks.Intltool bundle so that the necessary rule (MergeDesktopTranslations) doesn't even need to be explicitly specified:

appsdir = MakeInstallSubdirectory [ /config/install/datadir "applications" ]
appsinstaller = MakeCopyInstaller [ appsdir ]

f-spot.desktop = [ f-spot.desktop.in ] with [
        install = appsinstaller
        default = true
]

f-spot-view.desktop = [ f-spot-view.desktop.in ]  with [
        install = appsinstaller
        default = true
]

The rest of the toplevel Makefile.am is just bookkeeping:

CLEANFILES =                    \
        intltool-extract        \
        intltool-update         \
        intltool-merge

EXTRA_DIST =                    \
        MAINTAINERS             \
        intltool-extract.in     \
        intltool-merge.in       \
        intltool-update.in      \
        f-spot.spec             \
        $(desktop_in_files)     \
        $(desktop_files)

DISTCLEANFILES = \
        intltool-extract        \
        intltool-merge          \
        intltool-update         \
        $(desktop_files)

No analogue of this code is necessary in MBuild because its knowledge of file types automatically enables it to know what files should be cleaned and distributed.

We can now descend into the subdirectories of the f-spot source code. Following the Makefile.am, we start with FlickrNet and find:

LIBFLICKRNET_CSFILES =                          \
        $(srcdir)/AssemblyInfo.cs \
        $(srcdir)/Auth.cs \
        $(srcdir)/Blogs.cs \
	...
        $(srcdir)/UploadProgressEvent.cs \
        $(srcdir)/User.cs \
        $(srcdir)/Utils.cs

libflickrnetlibdir = $(libdir)/f-spot
libflickrnetlib_DATA =          \
        FlickrNet.dll

FlickrNet.dll: $(LIBFLICKRNET_CSFILES)
        $(CSC) -r:System.Web.dll -out:$@ /target:library $(LIBFLICKRNET_CSFILES)

all: FlickrNet.dll

EXTRA_DIST =                                                    \
        $(LIBFLICKRNET_CSFILES) \
        License.txt

CLEANFILES =                                                    \
        FlickrNet.dll

Once more, much of this code is essentially boilerplate. It can be expressed much more concisely with MBuild:

using [
        Core
        Core.Clr
        Languages.CSharp
]

FlickrNet.dll = [
        @FlickrNet.dll.sources
        /System.Web.dll
] with [
        install = /cslib-installer
]

License.txt = TextSource []

This file is made shorter, of course, by moving the list of source files into a separate .sources file. (Doing so is not necessary, but is more aesthetically pleasing to this author.) Note the reference to the /System.Web.dll target defined in the toplevel Buildfile. The matchers in the Languages.CSharp library would allow a bare reference to System.Web.dll, but then there would be two redundant checks for the DLL, one in the toplevel directory and one in FlickrNet. We also see that in some places, MBuild is no more elegant than automake: the latter's EXTRA_DIST variable is here approximated by defining License.txt as a do-nothing target. Finally, the install tag points to a new target that we define in the toplevel buildfile because it will likely be shared amongst several subdirectories:

flibdir = MakeInstallSubdirectory [ /config/install/libdir "f-spot" ]

lib-installer = MakeCCShlibOutputInstaller [ flibdir ]
cslib-installer = MakeCSharpCompilerOutputInstaller [ flibdir ]

Normally, instead of defining flibdir, one would use the predefined /config/install/pkglibdir, which evaluates to prefix/lib/package-compat-code. But we are seeking to maintain compatibility with the F-Spot Makefiles, so we define the directory and some installers manually.

The next subdirectory, icons, contains a bunch of PNG images that must be distributed with the source and one that gets installed.

noinst_DATA =                                   \
        f-spot-adjust-colors.png                \
        f-spot-browse.png                       \
        f-spot-camera.png                       \
	...
        f-spot.js                               \
        f-spot-simple.css                       \
        f-spot-simple-white.css

pixmapdir = $(datadir)/pixmaps
pixmap_DATA = f-spot-logo.png

EXTRA_DIST = $(noinst_DATA) $(pixmap_DATA)

Here, the MBuild language shows its current limitations:

using [
        Core
        Core.Install
]

pixmapdir = MakeInstallSubdirectory [
        /config/install/datadir
        "pixmaps"
]

pixmapinst = MakeCopyInstaller [ pixmapdir ]

f-spot-logo.png = BinSource [] with [
        install = pixmapinst
        default = true
]

f-spot-adjust-colors.png = BinSource []
f-spot-browse.png = BinSource []
f-spot-camera.png = BinSource []
...
f-spot.js = TextSource []
f-spot-simple.css = TextSource []
f-spot-simple-white.css = TextSource []

Because there is no builtin matcher for guessing what kind of file a .png file is, each one has to be explicitly declared as a binary file. (Updates to the MBuild language should make constructions like this obsolete.)

The next subdirectory, libeog, defines a C library:

SUBDIRS = cursors

INCLUDES =                                                      \
        -DG_LOG_DOMAIN=\"libfspoteog\"                          \
        -DDATADIR=\""$(datadir)"\"                              \
        -DLIBEOG_ETTORE_CHANGES=1                               \
        -I$(srcdir) -I$(top_srcdir)                             \
        -I$(top_srcdir)/src                                     \
        -I$(top_builddir)                                       \
        $(F_CFLAGS)                                             \
        $(LCMS_CFLAGS)

fspotlibdir = $(libdir)/f-spot
fspotlib_LTLIBRARIES = libfspoteog.la

libfspoteog_files =                             \
        access.c                                \
        access.h                                \
	...
        zoom.c                                  \
        zoom.h

libfspoteog_la_SOURCES = $(libfspoteog_files)

The cursors subdirectory just EXTRA_DISTs a few data files and can be skipped over in this discussion. The equivalent Buildfile for this directory starts with:

using [
        Languages.CrappyC
]

subdirs [ cursors ]

qdatadir = DefAddQuotes [ /config/install/datadir ]

defs = { LIBEOG_ETTORE_CHANGES = "1",
        G_LOG_DOMAIN = "\"libfspoteog\"",
        DATADIR = qdatadir
}

ccopts = MakeCCOptions [
        defs
        /fspot-pcflags
        /lcms-pcflags
]

libfspoteog.so = CompileShlib [
        @libfspoteog.so.sources
        /config.h
        ccopts
] with [
        install = /lib-installer
]

Here we define the C compiler options ccopts by combining a dictionary of #define constants (similar to what we saw with the Subst rule) and a set of opaque compiler flags obtained from pkg-config. We do not include the -I include path options because MBuild will automatically add such flags pointing to the directories in which the header file arguments to the CompileShlib rule can be found. This is something of a hack -- for instance, code may depend on foo/bar/bam.h but #include "bar/bam.h" in the source, while MBuild will blindly add a -Itop_srcdir/foo/bar argument to the compiler command line. Facts like this are why the current C language implementation is called CrappyC. Another hack is the DefAddQuotes rule, which just surrounds a string in quotation marks, thus turning what would be an identifier in C (/usr/share) into a string ("/usr/share"). Yet another problem is that limitations in the current bundle interface make it so that intermediate object files aren't generated; instead, every time libfspoteog.so needs to be recompiled, all of the source files must be compiled from scratch. And, most importantly, MBuild does not use libtool, so its shared-library compilation is most likely limited to Linux and GCC only at the moment, and probably yields incorrect results at times even then.

There is another section to libeog/Makefile.am:

libeog-marshal.h: libeog-marshal.list
        ( @GLIB_GENMARSHAL@ --prefix=libeog_marshal $(srcdir)/libeog-marshal.list --header > libeog-marshal.tmp \
        && mv libeog-marshal.tmp libeog-marshal.h ) \
        || ( rm -f libeog-marshal.tmp && exit 1 )

libeog-marshal.c: libeog-marshal.h
        ( @GLIB_GENMARSHAL@ --prefix=libeog_marshal $(srcdir)/libeog-marshal.list --body > libeog-marshal.tmp \
        && mv libeog-marshal.tmp libeog-marshal.c ) \
        || ( rm -f libeog-marshal.tmp && exit 1 )

MARSHAL_GENERATED = libeog-marshal.c libeog-marshal.h

BUILT_SOURCES = $(MARSHAL_GENERATED)
EXTRA_DIST = libeog-marshal.list

Again, code like this is easily dealt with in MBuild, because the build rules for glib-genmarshal can get first-class treatment, with all the same matching support that other, more commonly-used constructions get:

using [
        Languages.CrappyC
        Tools.GLibGenmarshal
]

...

libeog-marshal.c = [ libeog-marshal.list "libeog_marshal" ]
libeog-marshal.h = [ libeog-marshal.list "libeog_marshal" ]

The next subdirectory, libjpegtran, presents no new issues above what we've seen. The subdirectory after that one, libfspot, is also similar, although it exposes more weaknesses in the MBuild syntax. The Makefile.am of that directory is fairly uninteresting, so I will skip to showing you the corresponding Buildfile, with rough edges highlighted:

using [
        Languages.CrappyC
        Tools.GLibGenmarshal
]

defs = { LIBEOG_ETTORE_CHANGES = "1",
        G_LOG_DOMAIN = "\"libf\"",
        G_DISABLE_DEPRECATED = true,
        GTK_DISABLE_DEPRECATED = true,
        GDK_DISABLE_DEPRECATED = true,
        GNOME_DISABLE_DEPRECATED = true,

        # Problem: using AutoheaderCompat should somehow cause
	# something like this to be automatically added to the 
	# default C compiler flags
        HAVE_CONFIG_H = true
}

ccopts = MakeCCOptions [
        defs
        /fspot-pcflags
        /lcms-pcflags
        # Problem: haven't gotten around to implementing the
	# infrastructure needed to optionally add the -Werror 
	# flag that is included here.
]

topsrcdir = SourceDirHack [ "" ]

libfspot.so = CompileShlib [
        @libfspot.so.sources

        /config.h
        # Problem: This is the temporary ugly workaround to
	# avoid a failure in the naive scheme that MBuild uses 
	# to guess what -I flags to give to the compiler
	# (as discussed above).
	topsrcdir
        ccopts
        /exif-pclibs

        /libjpegtran/libfspotjpegtran.so
        /libeog/libfspoteog.so

	# Problem: Currently need to manually specify rpath
	# directories to feed to the linker.
        rpaths = /flibdir
] with [
        install = /lib-installer
]

f-marshal.h = [ f-marshal.list "f_marshal" ]
f-marshal.c = [ f-marshal.list "f_marshal" ]

It should be emphasized that all of the problem spots mentioned above are due to limitations in the Languages.CrappyC bundle, not in the MBuild architecture itself. With more work, the C language implementation should become much cleaner.

The subdirectories libgphoto2-sharp and semweb define C# libraries that are also nearly trivial to build. For instance, the Buildfile inside the former subdirectory is just:

using [
        Core.Clr
        Languages.CSharp
]

libgphoto2-sharp.dll = [
        @libgphoto2-sharp.dll.sources
        unsafe = true
        libgphoto2-sharp.dll.config
] with [
        install = /cslib-installer
]

The tools subdirectory contains some miscellaneous files that need to be installed. The Buildfile is again a little verbose:

using [
        Core
        Core.Install
        Core.Subst
        Frameworks.Intltool
]

# Translation-merged desktop file.

theme-installer = MakeExecutableCopyInstaller [ /gnome-screensaver-themedir ]

f-spot-screensaver.desktop = [ f-spot-screensaver.desktop.in ] with [
        install = theme-installer
]

# Photo importer wrapper.

f-spot-import = TextSource [] with [
        install = /config/install/bindir_installer
        default = true
]

# Screensaver wrapper script.

screensaver-installer = MakeExecutableCopyInstaller [ /gnome-screensaver-saverdir ]

f-spot-screensaver = TextSource [] with [
        install = screensaver-installer
        default = true
]

One thing that seems obvious in retrospect but is easy to forget is the application of the default tags. Many targets are not given this tag by default, and so in the usual circumstances they will only be built if referenced by other targets. This is usually desirable, but small utility files such as these tend not to be referenced by other targets and tend to be built with low-level rules that do not add the default tag to the target. (We can't assume that a target with an install tag should also have the default tag set to true, since it may be conditionally built.) The problem only manifests itself because running mbuild -I doesn't install these files, even though they're marked with an install tag. In fact, I only discovered these omissions by comparing a list of files installed by make install with one of the files installed by mbuild -I.

Next comes the po subdirectory. This directory is special in autotools projects; it has no Makefile.am, so we have no step-by-step transcription process. For the time being, the Buildfile presented below can be considered to be a kind of boilerplate; as with the autotools equivalent, the only real variable is the list of translations. Unfortunately, MBuild's implementation of the functionality of the gettext and intltool build suite is severely limited. Again, with more effort put into the Frameworks.Gettext and Frameworks.Intltool bundles, these deficiencies should be fixed. In the meantime, a bare minimum of functionality is available: .po files can be converted to .mo files and installed into the appropriate directories:

using [ 
	Core
	Frameworks.Gettext 
]

# We do this because our GETTEXT_PACKAGE is
# just "f-spot", not "f-spot-0.1" as the MBuild
# default is. If it were "f-spot-0.1", we could
# skip defining this installer and not have to
# manually override the install tag on each target.

mo-installer = MakeMOFileInstaller [ 
	/config/install/datadir
	package = /project/name 
]

POTFILES.in = TextSource []
POTFILES.skip = TextSource []

# Currently, each file must be declared separately!
# This is unfortunate but will be fixed.

bg.mo = [ bg.po ] with [ install = mo-installer ]
ca.mo = [ ca.po ] with [ install = mo-installer ]
...
zh_CN.mo = [ zh_CN.po ] with [ install = mo-installer ]
zh_TW.mo = [ zh_TW.po ] with [ install = mo-installer ]

Finally, we get to the last directory in the project: src. Within it the f-spot.exe executable is built. It puts the Languages.CSharp bundle through a bit of work, but C# is very easy to build, so the code is still quite easy. The Makefile.am is not very pretty:

CSC = mcs
CSFLAGS = -unsafe -debug -nowarn:0618 -nowarn:0169 -nowarn:0612 -d:TEST_METADATA

F_SPOT_CSDISTFILES =                            \
        $(srcdir)/Cairo/Cairo.cs                \
        $(srcdir)/Cairo/Surface.cs              \
        $(srcdir)/Cairo/FontOptions.cs          \
	...
        $(srcdir)/X3fFile.cs                    \
        $(srcdir)/XmpFile.cs                    \
        $(srcdir)/main.cs

ASSEMBLIES =                                    \
        -r:$(top_builddir)/libgphoto2-sharp/libgphoto2-sharp.dll   \
        -r:$(top_builddir)/semweb/SemWeb.dll    \
        -r:$(top_builddir)/FlickrNet/FlickrNet.dll      \
        -r:System.Data                          \
        -r:System.Web                           \
        -r:Mono.Data.SqliteClient               \
        -r:Mono.Posix                           \
        -r:Mono.Security                        \
        -r:ICSharpCode.SharpZipLib              \
        -pkg:dbus-sharp                         \
        -pkg:gtkhtml-sharp-2.0                  \
        -pkg:glade-sharp-2.0                    \
        -pkg:gnome-vfs-sharp-2.0                \
        -pkg:gconf-sharp-2.0

RESOURCES =                                                                             \
        -resource:$(top_srcdir)/icons/f-spot-adjust-colors.png,f-spot-adjust-colors.png         \
        -resource:$(top_srcdir)/icons/f-spot-browse.png,f-spot-browse.png               \
        -resource:$(top_srcdir)/icons/f-spot-crop.png,f-spot-crop.png                   \
	...
        -resource:$(top_srcdir)/icons/f-spot.js,f-spot.js       \
        -resource:$(srcdir)/dces.rdf,dces.rdf                   \
        -resource:$(srcdir)/f-spot.glade,f-spot.glade

fspotlibdir = $(libdir)/f-spot
fspotlib_DATA = f-spot.exe.config       \
                f-spot.exe

bin_SCRIPTS = f-spot

F_SPOT_CSFILES = $(F_SPOT_CSDISTFILES) Defines.cs

f-spot.exe: $(F_SPOT_CSFILES) f-spot.glade dces.rdf
        $(CSC) -out:$@ $(CSFLAGS) $(F_SPOT_CSFILES) $(ASSEMBLIES) $(RESOURCES)

all: f-spot.exe

The equivalent Buildfile is more concise:

using [
        Core
        Core.Clr
        Core.Install
        Core.Subst
        Languages.CSharp
        Tools.PkgConfig
]

# Don't need a full Buildfile in the Cairo subdir.
inside [ Cairo ] [ using [ Languages.CSharp ] ]

defs = { TEST_METADATA = true }

f-spot.exe = [
        @f-spot.exe.sources
        @f-spot.exe.resources
        f-spot.exe.config

        unsafe = true
        nowarn = "0618,0169,0612"
        defs

        /fspot-pclibs
        /System.Data.dll
        /System.Web.dll
        /Mono.Data.SqliteClient.dll
        /Mono.Posix.dll
        /Mono.Security.dll
        /ICSharpCode.SharpZipLib.dll
        /libgphoto2-sharp/libgphoto2-sharp.dll
        /semweb/SemWeb.dll
        /FlickrNet/FlickrNet.dll
] with [
        install = /cslib-installer
]

Here we have used the inside syntax, which makes it so we don't even have to write a Buildfile for the Cairo subdirectory: the matchers defined in the Languages.CSharp bundle are sufficient. The f-spot.exe.resources file can just list a bunch of files such as /icons/f-spot-crop.png: any listed file that is not C# source is added to the command line as a resource file, as we might wish. There are numerous compiler flags and assembly references, but they are mostly straightforward enough. One item to note is that we have replaced the -pkg:foo command-line arguments to mcs with the results of separate invocations of pkg-config saved in in the We must also remember to create the files generated from templates by config.status:

# Defines.cs.

defsubsts = {
        VERSION = /project/version,
        PACKAGE = /project/name,
        prefix = /config/install/prefix,
        libdir = /config/install/libdir,
        GNOME_ICON_THEME_PREFIX = /gnome-icon-theme-prefix
}

Defines.cs = Subst [
        Defines.cs.in
        typeref = main.cs # hacky
        defsubsts
]

# f-spot.exe.config

cfgsubsts = {
        expanded_libdir = /config/install/libdir,
        EXIF_SOVERSION = /exif-soversion
}

f-spot.exe.config = Subst [
        f-spot.exe.config.in
        typeref = /libgphoto2-sharp/libgphoto2-sharp.dll.config
        cfgsubsts
]

# f-spot wrapper

f-spot = Subst [
        f-spot.in
        defsubsts # Just reuse this
] with [
        install = /config/install/bindir_installer
        default = true
]

The typeref argument to the Subst rules is a moderately-sized hack. The Subst rule doesn't know what kinds of files it is working with, and so by default it just creates an output of type TextFile. However, when using the resulting file as an input to a complex rule such as CompileExe, the type of the file may matter: for instance, Defines.cs must be of type CSSource so that it gets added to the C# compiler command line; a more generic type will be treated as a resource to insert into the assembly, like the icons above. The typeref argument gives the Subst rule an "example" result of the appropriate type; if present, the rule returns a result of the same type as that argument.

It may have been tedious, but we've made it all the way through the F-Spot build system and translated everything. Of course, all the examples that I've shown above are the result of an iterative process: once the Buildfiles were written, I tweaked things until F-Spots installation and distributions created with the two systems were essentially identical. I also didn't describe how I wrote bundles to implement the functionality I needed as the migration process went along. Unsurprisingly, the latter activity actually took most of my time; however, as the library of bundles grows in size, writing new code should become less and less necessary. (By the way, a currently missing feature -- and major priority -- is to make it possible for custom bundles to be included with source distributions. Obviously the standard suite of MBuild rules can't be expected to cover the needs of every project out there, and no doubt some of the rules have bugs that will require workarounds. Custom rule bundles will at least make this problem addressable.)

Next: FIXME: Back to the Begining

Autotools' Greatest Hits

Since I decided to start writing MBuild, I've been collecting a list of the reasons why I felt it was necessary. Again, the GNU autotools system is extremely portable and has been a mainstay for me and many other hackers ... but it does have its rough edges:

make[3]: Entering directory `/home/peter/build/xine-lib/src/libtheora'
make[3]: Nothing to be done for `all'.
make[3]: Leaving directory `/home/peter/build/xine-lib/src/libtheora'
Making all in libspeex
/bin/sh: line 1: cd: libspeex: No such file or directory
make[2]: *** [all-recursive] Error 1
make[2]: Leaving directory `/home/peter/build/xine-lib/src'

The classic "New subdirectory in the build wasn't created because config.status wasn't rerun" problem. I believe there's some code in newer autoconfs to address this -- I recall seeing them running config.status without the --recheck parameter.

config.status: creating src/libvorbis/Makefile
config.status: creating src/libtheora/Makefile
config.status: creating src/libspeex/Makefile
config.status: error: cannot find input file: src/libspeex/Makefile.in

Oops! Forgot to rerun automake!

[peter@beta gal]$ automake-1.4
configure.in: 89: required file `./_AM_File,.in' not found
configure.in: 89: required file `./[$2],.in' not found
configure.in: 89: required file `./[$3])].in' not found

Oops! Now you ran the wrong version of automake! I like this one because of the sheer insanity of the error message it gives.

make -C src
make[1]: Entering directory `/home/peter/src/audacity-src-1.1.3/src'
ar rcs libaudacity.a obj/BlockFile.o obj/FileFormats.o obj/SampleFormat.o obj/blockfile/SimpleBlockFile.o obj/blockfile/PCMAliasBlockFile.o
make[1]: *** No rule to make target `../lib-src/libsamplerate/src/.libs/libsamplerate.a', needed by `../audacity'.  Stop.
make[1]: Leaving directory `/home/peter/src/audacity-src-1.1.3/src'
make: *** [audacity] Error 2

No idea what's going on here. Maybe static library builds were turned off and only libsamplerate.so was compiled?

cd . && /bin/sh /home/peter/cvs/mono/missing --run aclocal-1.6
cd . && \
  /bin/sh /home/peter/cvs/mono/missing --run automake-1.6 --foreign  Makefile
Makefile.am:5: bad macro name `'
Makefile.am:4: SUBDIRS multiply defined in condition TRUE
  SUBDIRS (User, where = Makefile.am:4) =
  {
    TRUE => mono doc docs scripts man data
  }
make: *** [Makefile.in] Error 1

Hm. Bad use of AM_CONDITIONALs? Some kind of CVS conflict marker causing problems?

source='error.c' object='error.lo' libtool=yes \
depfile='.deps/error.Plo' tmpdepfile='.deps/error.TPlo' \
depmode=gcc3 /bin/sh ../../depcomp \
/bin/sh ../../libtool --mode=compile gcc -DHAVE_CONFIG_H ...

Not an error per se. But these are the hoops that we need to jump through to compile a source file. Of course, C compilation is hard and MBuild can't even do it yet. Still, invoking two layers of shell scripts per source file is a performance hit.

checking whether to build static libraries... no
checking whether -lc should be explicitly linked in... no
creating libtool
checking gcc argument to enable C99... -std=c99
./configure: line 8431: syntax error near unexpected token `error'
./configure: line 8431: `GNOME_COMPILE_WARNINGS(error)'
make: *** [config.status] Error 2

My second-most common error. Bad aclocal flags. A classic.

/bin/sh ../libtool --mode=link gcc  -g -O2    -o libmonkey-media.la -rpath /usr/lib -export-dynamic monkey-media.lo monkey-media-stream-info.lo monkey-media-player-xine.lo monkey-media-player-gst.lo monkey-media-player-gst-tmp.lo monkey-media-audio-quality.lo monkey-media-audio-cd.lo sha1.lo monkey-media-musicbrainz.lo monkey-media-marshal.lo ../src/stream-info-impl/libstream-info-impl.la -pthread -Wl,--export-dynamic -lgnome-2 -lbonobo-2 -lgconf-2 -lgnomevfs-2 -lbonobo-activation -lORBit-2 -llinc -lgmodule-2.0 -ldl -lgobject-2.0 -lgthread-2.0 -lglib-2.0 -lxml2 -lz -lm   -Wl,--export-dynamic -pthread -lgstcontrol-0.6 -lgstgconf-0.6 -lgstreamer-0.6 -lgobject-2.0 -lgmodule-2.0 -ldl -lgthread-2.0 -lxml2 -lz -lm -lglib-2.0   -lmusicbrainz -lstdc++ -lm   -lz -L/usr/lib -logg -L/usr/lib -lvorbis -lm -lvorbisfile -lFLAC
grep: /usr/lib/liblinc.la: No such file or directory
/bin/sed: can't read /usr/lib/liblinc.la: No such file or directory
libtool: link: `/usr/lib/liblinc.la' is not a valid libtool archive
make[3]: *** [libmonkey-media.la] Error 1
make[3]: Leaving directory `/home/peter/cvs/monkey-media/src'

This one is mostly my fault, I admit. First I compiled my own ORBit so that .la files were install for all its shared libraries. Then at some point I replaced it with an RPM installation and the liblinc.la file got deleted one way or another. But in the meantime I had compiled another package that linked to liblinc.so, so a dependency on liblinc.la was embedded in its .la file. And when I tried to compile against that library, the dependency on the .la file failed. In other words, portable shared library compilation sucks.

gcc -DHAVE_CONFIG_H -I. -I../../../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/post/deinterlace/plugins -I../../../.. -I../../../../../../cvs/xine-lib -I../../../../include -I../../../../../../cvs/xine-lib/include -I../../../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src -I../../../../src/xine-engine -I../../../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/xine-engine -I../../../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/xine-utils -I../ -Wall -D_REENTRANT -D_FILE_OFFSET_BITS=64 -DXINE_COMPILE -O3 -pipe -fomit-frame-pointer -falign-functions=4 -falign-loops=4 -falign-jumps=4 -mpreferred-stack-boundary=2 -fexpensive-optimizations -fschedule-insns2 -fno-strict-aliasing -ffast-math -funroll-loops -finline-functions -mcpu=pentiumpro -I/usr/include/kde/artsc -c ../../../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/post/deinterlace/plugins/double.c -MT double.lo -MD -MP -MF .deps/double.TPlo  -DPIC -o double.lo
../../../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/post/deinterlace/plugins/double.c:27:20: speedy.h: No such file or directory
../../../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/post/deinterlace/plugins/double.c:28:25: deinterlace.h: No such file or directory

Somebody forgot to add a $(srcdir) prefix to their -I flags! This happens so often! Arg! I don't even try to do out-of-place builds anymore because pretty much no nontrivial project gets this right. I guess the xine folks don't make distcheck very often ...

source='../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/xine-utils/memcpy.c' object='memcpy.lo' libtool=yes \
depfile='.deps/memcpy.Plo' tmpdepfile='.deps/memcpy.TPlo' \
depmode=gcc3 /bin/sh ../../../../cvs/xine-lib/depcomp \
/bin/sh ../../libtool-nofpic --mode=compile gcc -DHAVE_CONFIG_H -I. -I../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/xine-utils -I../.. -I../../../../cvs/xine-lib -I../../include -I../../../../cvs/xine-lib/include -I../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src -I../../src/xine-engine -I../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/xine-engine -I../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/xine-utils     -I/usr/X11R6/include -Wchar-subscripts -Wmissing-declarations -Wmissing-prototypes -Wnested-externs -Wcast-align -Wpointer-arith -Wall -D_REENTRANT -D_FILE_OFFSET_BITS=64 -DXINE_COMPILE  -O3 -pipe -fomit-frame-pointer -falign-functions=4 -falign-loops=4 -falign-jumps=4  -mpreferred-stack-boundary=2 -fexpensive-optimizations -fschedule-insns2 -fno-strict-aliasing -ffast-math -funroll-loops -finline-functions -mcpu=pentiumpro   -I/usr/include/kde/artsc  -c -o memcpy.lo `test -f '../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/xine-utils/memcpy.c' || echo '../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/xine-utils/'`../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/xine-utils/memcpy.c
gcc -DHAVE_CONFIG_H -I. -I../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/xine-utils -I../.. -I../../../../cvs/xine-lib -I../../include -I../../../../cvs/xine-lib/include -I../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src -I../../src/xine-engine -I../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/xine-engine -I../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/xine-utils -I/usr/X11R6/include -Wchar-subscripts -Wmissing-declarations -Wmissing-prototypes -Wnested-externs -Wcast-align -Wpointer-arith -Wall -D_REENTRANT -D_FILE_OFFSET_BITS=64 -DXINE_COMPILE -O3 -pipe -fomit-frame-pointer -falign-functions=4 -falign-loops=4 -falign-jumps=4 -mpreferred-stack-boundary=2 -fexpensive-optimizations -fschedule-insns2 -fno-strict-aliasing -ffast-math -funroll-loops -finline-functions -mcpu=pentiumpro -I/usr/include/kde/artsc -c ../../../../cvs/xine-lib/src/xine-utils/memcpy.c -MT memcpy.lo -MD -MP -MF .deps/memcpy.TPlo  -DPIC -o memcpy.lo
mv: overwrite `.deps/memcpy.Plo', overriding mode 0664? y

No idea why this particular problem happens -- it's intermittent. Still, there's no fun like firing off a build and coming back an hour later, only to see that it froze after five minutes because a shell program tried to prompt you!

Running automake --gnu  ...
libmacl/Makefile.am:3: library used but `RANLIB' is undefined
libmacl/Makefile.am:3:
libmacl/Makefile.am:3: The usual way to define `RANLIB' is to add `AC_PROG_RANLIB'
libmacl/Makefile.am:3: to `configure.ac' and run `autoconf' again.
**Error**: automake failed.

Forgot to add AM_PROG_LIBTOOL, I think it was.

make[2]: Entering directory `/home/peter/src/rise-calc/libmacl'
cd .. && \
  /bin/sh /home/peter/src/rise-calc/missing --run automake-1.7 --gnu  libmacl/Makefile
libmacl/Makefile.am:13: use `libmacl_a_LIBADD', not `libmacl_a_LDADD'
make[2]: *** [Makefile.in] Error 1

Oops, forgot which of two extremely similar variable names to use.

make  all-recursive
make[1]: Entering directory `/home/peter/cvs/rhythmbox'
Making all in lib
make[2]: Entering directory `/home/peter/cvs/rhythmbox/lib'
Makefile:372: .deps/disclosure-widget.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:373: .deps/eel-gconf-extensions.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:374: .deps/eggtrayicon.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:375: .deps/gsequence.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:376: .deps/rb-atomic.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:377: .deps/rb-bonobo-helpers.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:378: .deps/rb-cut-and-paste-code.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:379: .deps/rb-debug.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:380: .deps/rb-dialog.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:381: .deps/rb-file-helpers.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:382: .deps/rb-file-monitor.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:383: .deps/rb-glade-helpers.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:384: .deps/rb-marshal.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:385: .deps/rb-playlist.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:386: .deps/rb-stock-icons.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:387: .deps/rb-string-helpers.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:388: .deps/rb-thread-helpers.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:389: .deps/rb-tree-dnd.Plo: No such file or directory
Makefile:390: .deps/rb-util.Plo: No such file or directory
make[2]: *** No rule to make target `.deps/rb-util.Plo'.  Stop.
make[2]: Leaving directory `/home/peter/cvs/rhythmbox/lib'
make[1]: *** [all-recursive] Error 1
make[1]: Leaving directory `/home/peter/cvs/rhythmbox'
make: *** [all] Error 2

I guess something went wrong in the black magic that's used to do dependency tracking of C source files. Again, I recognize that this is a hard problem to solve. I don't think I ever figured out what exactly was going wrong here -- rerunning automake fixed it, I think.

[peter@beta gst-plugins]$ /usr/bin/time automake-1.8
291.74user 1.91system 5:20.85elapsed 91%CPU (0avgtext+0avgdata 0maxresident)k
0inputs+0outputs (0major+27947minor)pagefaults 0swaps

On a 1.1 Ghz processor with 384 MB of RAM. gst-plugins has a lot of subdirectories; automake gets slow quickly in those conditions.

Why Bother Writing a New Build System?

I wrote MBuild from scratch. You might ask -- why bother? There are already plenty of build systems out there. Among others, you find make, automake, ant, Python distutils, jam, and the Linux kernel build system. And that is by no means a comprehensive list.

Design Goals

Now I can't say that I have used all of these systems extensively. But I've been a reluctant GNU autotools junkie for a while, and gave some other systems a try. I haven't found any with the right balance of features that I'd like to see, namely:

High-level design. The ability to express logic like "if $debug is true, compile all programs with debugging symbols" or "install all files as normal, but prefix all the destinations with /tmp/rpmbuild-1405". You can do this sort of stuff with automake, but after the umpteenth time that your out-of-place build fails because the Makefile.am author forgot the difference between $(srcdir) and $(builddir), you start losing patience.

Extensibility. The ability to add chunks of new logic to the build system in a way that scales well and integrates into the rest of the system. Something more robust than the fragments of shell script that we get with aclocal.

Flexibility. The ability to manage truly complicated builds. Systems like ant work well for most cases, but every so often you need build logic like "If I am building for a sparc machine and libgc is installed and the following test program demonstrates a bug, define GC_STACK_WORKAROUND when compiling mymem.c". (I am not very familiar with ant. Maybe I am not being fair to it here. But my understanding is that it does not support this sort of logic very well.) Oh, and good handling of build trees with subdirectories, unlike plain old make.

Interrogability. The ability to examine the build tree systematically. "Give me a list of all the executables compiled in this package." "Give me a list of all the source files in this package." "Give me a list of all the configuration options in this package." Then, instead of having some custom hack to generate an RPM spec file for a package, a nice external tool can do it cleanly. Or a software author can just have a better idea of the pieces that make up a large project.

Compactness. The ability to do all this without having to be insanely verbose. An XML syntax gets heavy awfully fast. Ideally, I should be able to say "program.exe: program.cs" and have the right thing happen.

Portability. This one is kind of tough -- make things too portable, and you've abstracted away a lot of useful integration. But it would be nice to be able to share a build system across all sorts of platforms.

(For a blunter rationale, see my collection of the Autotools' Greatest Hits.)

MBuild aspires to meet all these goals. I think it does a pretty good job right now, and can meet them all in the future. It takes advantage of some of the very good design choices made in the .NET framework to try and make a modular, extensible, fast system that encourages good build practices. The build is abstracted slightly more than in most systems, so that components can fit into a general framework that is known to work. But there are provisions to Do The Right Thing by default, so that you don't need a CS degree to write correct build files.

Design Decisions

Let me make it clear that I think all the other build tools that I've mentioned are competently written and I'm not denigrating the work that's been put into them. autoconf has been around forever and will last for years. And I don't envision MBuild as a "make replacement": for some tasks, make is fine. (See /var/yp/Makefile). But for the task of building software, I don't like the overall design that the existing build tools have, and I think MBuild has a better approach. Specifically, I made the following decisions when writing MBuild:

The system has to track dependencies on more than just files. Say you have the following Makefile fragment:

VERSION=0.10

myprogram: main.c test.c
	gcc -o myprogram -DVERSION=$(VERSION) main.c test.c

If you change the value of $(VERSION), make isn't smart enough to recompile for you. If the dependency on $(VERSION) can be tracked by the build software, this problem is avoided.

The system must make it so you don't have to write your own rules. If you wanted to write the canonical build example

myprogram: main.c test.c
	gcc -o myprogram -DVERSION=$(VERSION) main.c test.c

in C-like syntax, you'd end up saying

myprogram = compile_c_program (main.c, test.c, $(VERSION));

Or something along those lines. And yet make forces you to effectively write out the code for compile_c_program every time you want to call it. That's nuts.

The system must make it so you can write your own rules. Automake solves the "no canned rules" problem that make has. But there's no way to extend automake's library of rules! You end up with monstrosities like the intltools aclocal macros, which expand out to Makefile rules:

desktop_DATA = myprogram.desktop

@INTLTOOL_DESKTOP_RULE@

becomes

desktop_DATA = myprogram.desktop

%.desktop:   %.desktop.in   $(INTLTOOL_MERGE) $(wildcard $(top_srcdir)/po/*.po) ; LC_ALL=C $(INTLTOOL_MERGE) $(top_srcdir)/po $< [$]@ -d -u -c $(top_builddir)/po/.intltool-merge-cache'

(And of course it took the intltool hackers about four tries to get this expansion to work in a way that interacted nicely with all the other elements of the GNU autotools chain.) Apparently this sort of pluggable functionality is on the way with automake, though it remains to be seen how well it will work. Seeing as automake is a gigantic Perl script, I'm not getting my hopes up. (No slur on Tom Tromey or the other authors of automake; I'm just a Perl hater.)

The most important input to the system is the dependency. Every time you say that "A depends on B", you're encoding a piece of very important information -- that dependency isn't just there for fun, there's some reason why it exists. The build system should be able to exploit this fact to maximum effect.

The system should be unified. At least three different languages go into the GNU autotools setup. The system works, but every so often M4 quoting rules bite you in the ass. All relevant aspects of the build system should be based on a single foundation that provides the basics but isn't overly restrictive.

MBuild tries to meet all of these needs. But let's look at some concrete examples first, putting the mbuild command-line client through its paces.

Next: A First Look at MBuild